<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cures vvithout care, or A summons to all such who finde little or no helpe by the use of ordinary physick to repaire to the northerne Spaw Wherein by many presidents of a few late yeares, it is evidenced to the world, that infirmities in their owne nature desperate and of long continuance have received perfect recovery, by vertue of minerall waters neare Knaresborow in the West-riding of Yorkeshire. Also a description of the said water, and of other rare and usefull springs adjoyning, the nature and efficacie of the minerals contained in them, with other not impertinent notes. Faithfully collected for the publique good by M. St.</title>
            <author>Stanhope, Michael.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852997</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1188:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cures vvithout care, or A summons to all such who finde little or no helpe by the use of ordinary physick to repaire to the northerne Spaw Wherein by many presidents of a few late yeares, it is evidenced to the world, that infirmities in their owne nature desperate and of long continuance have received perfect recovery, by vertue of minerall waters neare Knaresborow in the West-riding of Yorkeshire. Also a description of the said water, and of other rare and usefull springs adjoyning, the nature and efficacie of the minerals contained in them, with other not impertinent notes. Faithfully collected for the publique good by M. St.</title>
                  <author>Stanhope, Michael.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Mich. Stanhope.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Knaresborough --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:1"/>
            <p>CVRES WITHOVT CARE, OR A SVMMONS TO ALL SVCH WHO FINDE LITTLE OR no helpe by the uſe of ordinary phyſick to repaire to the <hi>Northerne Spaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN By many preſidents of a few late yeares, it is evidenced to the world, that infirmities in their owne nature deſperate and of long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance have received perfect recovery, By vertue of Minerall waters neare <hi>Knaresborow</hi> in the Weſt-riding of <hi>Yorkeſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo a deſcription of the ſaid water, and of other rare and uſefull ſprings adjoyning, the nature and efficacie of the Minerals contained in them, with other not impertinent notes.</p>
            <p>Faithfully collected for the publique good by <hi>M. St.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tibul.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>— felix quicunque dolore</l>
               <l>Alterius diſces poſſe carere tuo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling in Red-croſſe-ſtreet. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE THOMAS LORD WENTWORTH of <hi>Wentwoth Woodhouſe,</hi> Baron <hi>Newmarch</hi> and <hi>Overſley,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Wentworth,</hi> Lord Preſident of his Majeſties Councel eſtabliſhed in the <hi>North,</hi> Lord Leiftenant of the County of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Lord Deputy of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and one of his Majeſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privie Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Had once (I confeſſe raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) given leave that this ſmall Treatiſe ſhould put on the Printers livery with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the convoy of a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting paſſe. But as I caſt my laſt eye upon it, it appeared to me like a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man ready to encounter an army. For there are not more men, then vollies of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious ſhot, that ſtand ready prepared to batter any novelty. This conſideration forc't
<pb facs="tcp:177769:3"/> me ſuddenly to looke out for a defenſative guard, againſt the daring boldneſſe of this criticall age. Wherein I was not long unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. For who is hee that caſts his daze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led eye on the brightneſſe of your redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled rayes of honour, or fixeth his ſerious thoughts on your Lordſhips ſuperintenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in publique affaires (dilating it ſelfe not onely from the north to the ſouth, but ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding its influence as farre as the regall eye of great Brittaine doth command) and findes not in himſelfe a tye to offer upon the altar of your Lordſhips meriting greatneſſe an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his reſpect? And who ſo fit to patronize theſe waters (not more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their effects, then happy that they are ſeated where your iudicious government doth bleſſe the country) then your Lordſhip, whoſe eminency in thoſe parts, doth of right challenge the appropriation of what rariety ſoever the liſtes of the <hi>North</hi> doth empale? Be pleaſed therefore (in all accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments moſt noble Lord) to admit of theſe waters (which even as they neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to your ſpacious revenues claime an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb facs="tcp:177769:3"/> in your ſafegard) ſubmitting to your honours ſhielding protection, and favorable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accept of the tender of his moſt humble ſervice, who would willingly improve his beſt abilleties actually to be honoured with the title of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble ſervant, <hi>Mich. Stanhope.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is plaine, I have not the leaſt intent to gull thee in magnefying the <hi>Northerne Spaw,</hi> nor yet to tyrannize over thee, by confining, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating thy beliefe within the circle of my bare relation, by a generall avernment of what I write; for in nomination the parties who have received benefit by the water, I open unto thee a large field for thy ſatisfaction. If it doth appeare to thee (by conferring with any of them) that I have erred in ſome circumſtances, ſtumble not at it. So long as I retaine the ſubſtance, it matters not for the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. Nor thinke it ſtrange that I omit others who have made uſe of the water, ſince it proceedes not out of ignorance of what hath paſt, but out of a tender regard I have not to burthen thy patience: ſuppoſing that the culling forth of the moſt remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inſtances, would bee as ſatisfactorie to the judicious, as many heapes of examples. My purpoſe aymeth rather at a compendious realtie of things, then multiplicity of stories. Moſt of the parties I know, and have had conference with them: the reſt I have received from ſuch authenticall teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that I doubt not but their information, is of ſufficient vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie to beget an undoubted confidence of their truths.</p>
            <p>If any of thoſe mentioned in the following diſcourſe (out of a nice ſcrupulocitie) thinke themſelves diſparaged by particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing their names, I am ſorry that they ſhould be ſo ignorantly curious ſince former times have afforded many preſidents (writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by way of Councell, ſuch as are thoſe of <hi>Fernelius, Crato,</hi> and many others) wherein diverſe of eminent quality (beſides their names) have their diſeaſes anotamiſed, without the leaſt conceived jealouſie of their reputations. They ought rather to bleſſe God, who hath in mercy vouchſafed them ſuch eaſie meanes of their recovery, and glad themſelues, that others by their example may be encouraged to have have recourſe to the water for their reliefe.</p>
            <p>It may be, it is exſpected that I ſhould ſatisfie the learned in
<pb facs="tcp:177769:4"/> one particular, namely, what aſſurance I can give that this our <hi>Spaw</hi> doth partake with Vitriol, and Iron, which once confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, there will neceſſarily follow an apparant probability of its ample performance of all and more then ſhall fall within the compaſſe of the following relations. This I foreſeeing neceſſarily premiſing the concluſion, I deſire that they would pleaſe to take for proofe of the infallibility of Vitriol the taſte of the water, which is very acide, and rough upon the pallate, in plainer Engliſh, ynkiſh, and ſo like to Vitrioll or Copperes (called an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently <hi>Attramentum ſutorium</hi>) that there is little or no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the taſte of the water and the ſubſtance of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioll touched with the tongue; or a drop of the oyle thereof mixed with a little water. Beſides, take a glaſſe of the water (which in it ſelfe is tranſlucid and very cleare, equaling the choiceſt ſpring) let the quantity be a pinte or thereabout, put to it ſo much Gall in powder as will cover our common far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſtirre it never ſo little, and the water receiveth a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Clarret dye. Or take a greene Oake ſticke, bruiſe it at the end, and with it ſtirre the like quantity of water, and within a ſmall ſpace it is turned into a pure Saphir blew, or (ſtanding a while with the ſticke in it) to a Violet colour, both which hath beene often tryed. As for iron we account it a demonſtrative note, the diſcollering of the earth and ſtones where the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the ſpring runnes: for it makes the channell red, which proceedes (as may be ſuppoſed) from <hi>Rubrique,</hi> otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>mater ferri.</hi> And the better to confirme that the water is no ſtranger to iron, it is very well knowne that the whole ſoyle where this water riſeth is full of iron ſtone, the plenty whereof hath beene ſuch, that the working of iron ſtone hath beene a meanes to exhauſt a world of wood growing in that part, there being yet to ſee the remainder of a great iron worke within halfe a mile of the ſpring. Nor is the iron ſtone ſo concealed but by digging in moſt places it is eaſily found, much of it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in broaken bankes, and in the ſurface of the earth. I might boldly adde hereunto (for further proofe) the diſcolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſtooles of ſuch as drinke the water, giving them a blacn or deep green dye, a common obſerved note in iron waters,
<pb facs="tcp:177769:5"/> as alſo the operation of the water in all manner of obſtructions, wherein (who knowes not) that iron doth claime an unparale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led excellency, but the enſuing diſcourſe will make this good. Other notes an exact mineralliſt would eaſily produce, to whoſe diſcuſſing and diſquiſition I willingly leaue matters of this nature, they being improper for the ſpheare, both of my ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity and profeſſion.</p>
            <p>How it comes to paſſe that theſe waters are thus vertuall, the learned can eaſily make appeare; for the mineralls that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixe with them once granted, from their natures will ariſe abundant ſatisfaction to all that are rationall of their excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe. As ſhortly thus. <hi>Sulphur</hi> (ſay they that write of it) attracts, reſolves, mollefieth, diſcuſſeth, cooles and dries.</p>
            <p>Salt (whereof our Sulphur ſpring containes a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion) is aſtringent, detergent, purging, diſperſing, attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, preſerving from putrefaction.</p>
            <p>Yron ſaith (our learned <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Iordan</hi>) hath an opening or deopilating quality, and an aſtringent alſo.</p>
            <p>Vitrioll (according to <hi>Diaſcorides</hi>) doth heate and binde. It hath an exceeding ſubtilty of parts ſaith <hi>Tho. Iordanus,</hi> and is of a penetrative quality.</p>
            <p>From their abſtesſive and inciſive qualities, it is noted that theſe waters doe looſen and ſcatter viſcuous and clammy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they attenuate the groſſe, and after by their penetrative quality, the Liver, Spleene, the meſeraique veines, reines, and other partes are deopilated, and by this meanes freed from ſuch diſeaſes as proceede from obſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Turner</hi> in his diſcourſe of Baths and minerall waters ſaith, that waters partaking of iron and Brimſtone, coole and dry, that they are proper for all ſoares of the Kidneyes and Bladder, they both prevent and cure the ſtrangury, Dry up rumes, are good for them that are ſhort winded or ſtopped in the breaſt, that ſpit bloud, they cure the greene ſickneſſe, are very fit for cold flegmatick men that would gladly have chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and have none; and ſo for women whoſe default doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from too much moiſtneſſe of the matrixe, they are good by drinke or gliſter againſt wormes, and fit to allay the paines in the ſmall guts.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:5"/>
            <p>He ſaith alſo that where iron beareth the chiefe rule (as it doth in our <hi>Spaw</hi>) ſuch waters are excellent for all manner of itch; hardneſſe of the milt, diſeaſes of the joynts, ſtiffeneſſe of the ſinewes, cramps proceeding of moiſtneſſe, numneſſe or ſleepineſſe in any part, dizineſſe of the head, the flixe, weake Kidneyes, piſſing of blood, heate of urine, the oft, too much, and unwilling making of water, gnawings, and paines in the belly.</p>
            <p>Waters (ſaith <hi>Mounſieur Pigray</hi> in the obſervations of the <hi>German Spaw</hi>) whereunto ours are little (I am but too mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt) inferiour, partaking of iron and vitrioll; revive the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, provoke appetite, facilitate digeſtion, free from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of obſtructions; they oppoſe wonderfully the generatton of the ſtone, and hinder the knitting of the gravell with the glu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous raw, and veſcuous humor. The Hermetically learned (ſaith <hi>Hermannius Wolfus</hi> in his <hi>tractate de viribus, &amp; uſu aquarum in Agro Caſſellano</hi>) note that Vitroline waters have a faculty of mundefying and purging all the parts of the hody, corroborating the braine, curing the Epilepſie, exciting the appetite, killing all ſorts of wormes, oppoſing the Palſey, Dropſie, Iaundiſe, breeding of the ſtone, ſuffocation of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, all inward oppilations, prevent the goute, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excellent qualities as may appeare in that his diſcourſe in the third chapter. Which faculties joyned with the other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, our waters partaking with them all, how uſefull theſe theſe waters may be, I leave to the conſideration of thoſe who are able to deduce particular inſtances from aſſured generall grounds. With theſe authors agree many learned ones, whoſe opinions I ſpare to tranſcribe, being very unwilling to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>; my ſelfe in the diſcourſe of theſe miſteries, whereby I may be thought ſaucely to ſnatch the pen out of the Doctors hand, to whom I leave thee for further ſatisfaction, the former au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities being ſufficient to grace our waters and confirme their vertue.</p>
            <p>They who with ſome violence put me upon this taske of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending to the generall notice this water, with its conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſprings, might (if they had pleaſed) have undertaken it
<pb facs="tcp:177769:6"/> with a more plaucible entertainment: but their profeſſion tending to preſcribe to thoſe who are to uſe the water (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) cauſed them to forbeare their paines, leaſt a relation from them might ſeeme to reflect at their particular interest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein I am altogether free.</p>
            <p>Omitting therefore all further apollogies, (for I feare the gates are growne too great for the Citty) rather then the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſhould not bee benefitted, I have adventured bluntly to ſtep upon the ſtage. Wherein if I may but be ſo happy, as by my weake (though willing) pen to invite any to the water for their good, and that I may receive of thee (that which an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intention may challenge) the Plaudite of a favourablr ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, I ſhall thinke my ſmall paines largely recompenced, and ſhall wiſh thee all ſucceſſe in the uſe of theſe waters, and thy being partaker of that water, whereof whoſoever drinkes ſhall never after be a thirſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="catalogue_of_persons">
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:6"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſuch perſons as have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved benefit or cure by Minerall waters of <hi>Knaresborow</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Of the Stone</head>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                  <hi>Rolfe</hi> of <hi>Hadley</hi> in ihe County of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> pag. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Curra</hi> of <hi>Whardale</hi> of 50. yeares. p. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Rowley</hi> of <hi>Linton,</hi> aged 60. yeares, p. 7.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                  <hi>May</hi> of <hi>Yorke,</hi> very old, p. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Shan</hi> of <hi>Medley,</hi> p. 13.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of Vlcers in Kidneis</head>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                  <hi>Barker</hi> of <hi>Doare,</hi> p. 7.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                  <hi>Ellis</hi> of <hi>Beaverly,</hi> cured of the like,</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of Mallencholly.</head>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Sacheveril</hi> of <hi>Darbiſhire,</hi> p. 8.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                  <hi>Ayre</hi> of <hi>Rampton,</hi> p. 9.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of ſhortneſſe of Breath.</head>
               <item>One <hi>Wallis,</hi> aged 50. yeares, p. 14.</item>
               <item>The Counteſſe of <hi>Buchingham,</hi> p. 14.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of weakneſſe in the Limmes.</head>
               <item>M <hi>Foules</hi> an Advocate of <hi>Scotland</hi> p. 11.</item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Vaviſour</hi> p. 13.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of Swelling</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maude Bogge,</hi> aged 50. yeares. p. 18.</item>
               <item>A poore man of the like, p. 18.</item>
               <item>A poore woman of the like in her breaſt, p. 19.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of ſeverall other infirmities.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Tompſon</hi> of the Hecticke Feaver, p. 10.</item>
               <item>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Rauden</hi> of a ſtrange ſort of wormes, p. 12.</item>
               <item>The Lady <hi>Hoyle,</hi> a ſtrange cure, p. 15.</item>
               <item>A poore Boy of the Falling-ſickneſſe, p. 16.</item>
               <item>One <hi>Smith</hi> a Shoomaker of the Scurvey, p. 19.</item>
               <item>A Miniſter of a violent Flixe, with many others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177769:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177769:7"/>
            <head>A RELATION OF CERTAINE PARTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVLAR CVRES DONE BY Vertue of Minerall waters neare <hi>Knares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow</hi> in the weſt-riding of the <hi>County of</hi> Yorkſhire</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EFORE entrance be made into the inſuing narrations, it will not be amiſſe for the ſatisfaction of ſuch who are meere ſtrangers to the knowledge of theſe waters, to let them know, that it is now full ſixe yeares ſince notice hath beene given to the world by a booke called <hi>Spadacrene</hi> or the Engliſh <hi>Spaw</hi> (written by Doctor <hi>Deane</hi> a learned Phyſitian of the City of <hi>Yorke</hi>) of certaine minerall waters ſeated in the Forreſt of <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> in the weſt riding of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> Since which time divers have repaired to them from remote places (according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177769:8"/> neceſſities to experement them, invited by the Doctors promiſed probabilities of their uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full operations. What hath beene the event and ſucceſſe, I have vndertaken to preſent to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique view, beginning firſt with a ſhort Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the waters diſcriptions which I know can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be expected.</p>
            <p>Of divers Springs that (as it were) preſſe which ſhould be firſt ſeene, within a ſmall diſtance one of another (ſome whereof being of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, differing onely <hi>Secundum magis et minus,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers varying in their compoſures diſpenſed and ordered by the carefull and vnimitable hand of provident nature) there are two moſt remarque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, which beyond expectation have advanced themſelves by their admirable faculties. The one is now called the <hi>Spaw,</hi> but formerly knowne by the name of the <hi>Tuit</hi> well, deriving its vertue principally from iron and vittriall. This hath bin long knowne, and of late hath beene much fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, bleſſing many that have made uſe of it with extraordinary good effects. It is diſtant from <hi>Knaresborow</hi> (being a place very apt to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date ſtrangers plentifully both for dyet and lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging) about a mile and a halfe. Though the ſoile where this Spring riſeth doth afford divers of the like nature, yet till of late there hath not any bin ſo induſtrious as to ſearch which is it that may iuſtly challenge the precedence. This laſt Summer 1631. it was my hap to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a new Spring diſtancing it ſelfe about a quarter of a mile from the other, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177769:8"/> it had beene trenched, and opened, did give ſatisfaction to all (that were not partiall) that it deſerves a better degree of eſtimation then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I would be loath to diſparage the old ſpring, yet I muſt take leave to preſume that this late found Spring doth exceed the other in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars, which whether they give lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to it by way of excellency or no, I ſubmit to the iudgement of the learned.</p>
            <p>Firſt for the Scituation, it is placed in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a great hill, the ground round about it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very firme, whereby it giveth advantage of faire dry walkes, wherein the other is very defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, for that riſing in a flat, the ground neare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it is boggye, to the preiudice of the water, confining the company that reſort to it within too narrow a compaſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the triall with the Gall, the colour of the new Spring changeth more haſtily, and the water admits of a deeper dye then the other.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, divers who have tryed this water vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily affirme that they can with more eaſe, and with leſſe nauciouſneſſe to the ſtomach, drink 20. glaſſes of it, then 14 of the other, which if I miſtake not) ſhewes a great meaſure of repleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Spirits.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, being carried as farre as the Citty of <hi>Yorke,</hi> it retaineth as full and as briſque a taſte there, as the other doth at the Spring head, and tryed ſo farre off with the Gall, it lookes with a bould ruddy face upon the beholder: whereas the other abates much of its native taſte being
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177769:9"/> brought to the Citty, and lookes but with a pale ſhamfac't bluſh, having received the admixture of the powder of the Gall. So that there is no doubt but this water may be tranſported to very good uſe, ſuppoſing the bottells to be very well ſtopt, which is a caution to be neceſſarily obſerved by all thoſe that will ſend for the water, whereby the way I would wiſh ſuch as have the water brought to them, to make uſe rather of glaſſe, then of ſtone bottels, but as for woodden ones (which I have ſeene fild with the water) in regard of the pooreneſſe of that ſubſtance, it is but loſt labour to uſe them, the life of the water conſiſting cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſpirits, which are of ſuch a nimble agile nature, that they are very apt to tranſpire, and ſcorne to be impriſoned in woodden walls.</p>
            <p>Laſtly it is moſt aparant that this late fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpring hath an admixture of Brimſtone, beſides the iron and vitriall, which I take to bee an aditament of worth and nobleneſſe, for the more variety of minerall (ſay the beſt obſervers of theſe waters) the more proper for diverſity of diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pers: &amp; that ſulpher ſprings are profitable in the infirmities of the Lungs, there is no doubt to bee made, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo a healing quallitie, and therefore fitly appliable to any inward vlcerated part by which the water ſhall paſſe. This ſpring upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (proving in all points deſirable) excellent, was this laſt ſummer ſet with ſtone, where it now ſtands upon its triall, and doth boldly challenge any whatſoever of the ſame nature.</p>
            <p>Neighboring to this, there are three other dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177769:9"/> ſprings not a mile diſtant one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein Sulpher (not in its ſubſtance but vapour) doth predominate. One of them hath beene long knowne by the name of the ſtinking well (for though the water bee very cleare, yet it is moſt true that it hath (ſcarce) a ſufferable ſent, whereby it hath beene found by them that ſought it not. It is actually cold, and beſides its ſulpherous quallitie (which is in a very high de, gree) it is exceeding ſalt, ſo that a pottle of it being evaporated, there will be found aboue halfe an ounce of perfect ſalt remaining. There is another not yeelding at all to this in its ſulpheriouſneſſe, but it is not perceivably ſalt at all. A third that is both ſulpherous, and ſalt, but in a more remiſſe degree. The firſt of theſe three is onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and hath acted its part with great approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the other two are neglected, though I am perſwaded they may be found (for ſome bodies) more apt and proper then the former, were they iudiciouſly examined.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaw</hi> ſprings though they uſually chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge (as doth the <hi>Spaw</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> which is the reaſon we give them the ſame name) a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity in eaſing and curing (ſuch as are curable of the ſtone, and gravell, as alſo in opening the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the Spleane, and allaying all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly effects and paſſions, yet it will appeare by the ſubſequent diſcourſe and relations, that this kind of water hath other rare and ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences and opperations, which hath procured no ſmall wonder in thoſe who have obſerved the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects!
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177769:10"/> The particular inſtances whereof (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any longer ſuſpending thy expectation, I now intend to enter upon, beginning firſt with the cure and alleviation of the ſtone and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtempers incident to the Kidneys and Reines.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1626. M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Rolf</hi> of Hadley in the County of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> having occaſion to give a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit to ſome of her neare friends in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few weekes of her ſtay there, ſhee found her ſelfe ſuddenly ſurpriſed with extraordinary ſharp fits, which by there ſymptomes did manifeſtly appeare to be the ſtone. Hereupon ſhe applyed her ſelfe to the Phyſitians adviſe, but finding lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no eaſe by their preſcriptions (though pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ones) ſhe was perſwaded to try the new water at <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> where ſhe had not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued aboue a fortnight, but ſhe voyded many ſtones, to the number of a hundred, bigger and leſſe, whereby ſhee was quit of all her paine, and hath ever ſince continued in health, free from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of anoyance in that kind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Curra</hi> of <hi>Whardale</hi> in the weſterne parts of <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> ſervant to S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Peter Middleton,</hi> about the age of 50. yeares, having ſuffered much pain for divers yeares, his fits of the ſtone being ſo violent that he was not able to ride on horſeback, or to lye in his bed an houre together without ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, nothing that he could take affording him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eaſe, he went at laſt to the <hi>Spaw</hi> ſpring, where having drunke the water about a month, he voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded divers ſtones, ſome whereof he hath to ſhew
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177769:10"/> being bigger then a great Pea. Hee returned home eaſed of all his paine, hee recovered his ſtrength, and is now well able to ride about his occaſions without any diſturbance, nor hath hee ever ſince (being now 3. yeares) had any fits wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of complaint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Rowley</hi> of <hi>Linton,</hi> neare <hi>Weatherby</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> of the age of 60. yeares, much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed a long time with the ſtopping of his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by his repaire to the <hi>Spaw</hi> voyded much gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, and from that time was no more troubled ſo long as he lived.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Barker</hi> of <hi>Doare</hi> in <hi>Darbeſhire</hi> about the age of 34. yeares, had a dangerous ulcer in her Kidney, beſides a very obſtructed body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe was brought ſo low, that ſhe was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to go without the ſupport of one or two; her ſtomack had loſt its appetite, not able through weakeneſſe to diſgeſt any meate, no nor the moſt apt broathes that could be made, ſo that ſhe was forced to ſuſtaine nature by returning to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant pap. In this weake and deſperate condition (having formerly not ſpared to uſe all the helpes that could be deviſed by the Phyſitian) ſhe was gently brought to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> not expecting (as ſhe told me her ſelfe) to be recovered, onely ſhe thought it not fit to be wanting to any meanes that might bee propounded. It pleaſed God to give ſuch a bleſſing in the uſe of the water (which ſhe dayly drunke as well as ſhee was able) that within a few dayes there came from her an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible deale of putrid matter, which gave her
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177769:11"/> ſuch eaſe, that by degrees ſhe gathered ſtrength, her inward parts were deopilated, her ſtomack reſtored, and within the compaſſe of 5. weekes ſhe was (to the wonder of all that had taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of her) reduced to a moſt apparent ſtate of health and ability of body. I ſeeing her this ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, 1631. at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> (for it was the foregoing yeare ſhee had received her cure, and this yeare came onely to the water to confirme her ſelfe) could not but admire to behold ſo freſh a looke, and ſo well liking a body, conſidering the report of her former exceeding weakeneſſe.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay it were time loſt, but it might be better ſpent then to multiply all the knowne examples in this kinde, the foregoing ones being of ſufficient proofe to make good the waters effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catious uſe in the infirmity of the ſtone. Not that I am to ſeeke for more, for I might (but that I willingly avoyd ſuperfluous tediouſneſſe) adde to the other.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Ellis</hi> wife to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Ellis</hi> Miniſter at Beaver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who received a wondrous cure in the like ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerated part.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>May</hi> a Cittizens wife of <hi>Yorke,</hi> who after many yeares trouble (being of great age) was abſolutely freed from her long continued fits of the ſtone with diverſe others whom I purpoſely omit (nothing being more ordinary) that others may come into play (though of a differing kinde, yet) of remarkeable note.</p>
            <p>For Melancholy and Splenetique effects, there are few or none (that I have ever yet heard of)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177769:11"/> who have repaired to this <hi>Spaw</hi> water, but have found extraordinary eaſe, and a great abatement of thoſe diſturbances which are the ordinary unwelcome attendants of that diſtemper.</p>
            <p>Amongſt others, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Sacheveril</hi> of <hi>Darbiſhire</hi> (hearing of this <hi>Spaw</hi> water) came to <hi>Yorke</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with Dr. <hi>Deane,</hi> who after hee had fitly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared his body (a rule groſſely omitted by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) ſent him <hi>Knaresborow</hi> to drinke of the water, being in the yeare, 1630. to his great releife. For whereas hee had beene exceedingly long time perplexed with many fearefull paſſions, and upon ſleight occaſions, apt to entertaine horrid and aſtoniſhing imaginations; the ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of that deſeaſe called <hi>Hypochondriaca paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio</hi>) he returned to <hi>Yorke</hi> to give D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Deane</hi> thanks for his ſending him to the water, profeſſing his ſpirits to be much cheared, his fancy cleared from all cloudy and miſty conceits, which his very looke and inſpecttion did witneſſe, and ſo he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home continuing ever ſince in a conſtant tenor of a quiet and uninterrupted condition.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Ayre</hi> wife to M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Anthony Ayre</hi> of <hi>Rampton,</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> a gentlewoman of much worth and eſteeme for her aproved vertue, and all other requiſites that give luſter to her ſexe, had (with the expence of much money) tryed what could be done in the taming and qualifying of that ſame dull malancholly humor, her ſelfe not unſeene (as in many rare ſecrets ſo) in curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous receits of that kinde, at length grew weary in trying concluſions, receiving little or no benefit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177769:12"/> by any. She was drawne at laſt by report of the <hi>Yorkeſhire Spaw,</hi> to try the effects of it, which was in the yeare 1629. where ſhee found more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and eaſe by one moneths uſe of the water, then ſhe could ever receive by all the beſt adviſe her money could purchaſe.</p>
            <p>Others I have knowne affected or rather af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted in this kinde, who have acknowledged to have received great benefit by this water, whoſe names and ſtories I ſpare the forenamed being ſufficient inſtances of the powerfull effect of this water in moderating this ſame <hi>Ludibrium Medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> the melancholly humor.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now preſent a miſſellanie of other cures, or rather wonders, worthy the ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the learned, and the admiration of all.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>William Tompſon</hi> Poſtmaſter of <hi>Weatherby</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> had continued deſperately ſicke of a hectick feaver 28. weeks, living then in <hi>Cambridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> He had uſed the advice of the beſt Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians in thoſe parts, and was at laſt given over as a man paſt hope, his weakeneſſe being ſuch that he went not to the ſtoole in all that time, but by the helpe of a ſuppoſitory, or the like meanes. In this poore eſtate (hearing of this water) hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventureth in the depth of winter (a moſt unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable time by the conſent of all thoſe who write of the uſe of theſe kinde of waters) to experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them, and ſo with ſome difficulty he was brought to <hi>Weatherby</hi> being diſtant from <hi>Knares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow</hi> foure miles. Having reſted a day or two, he began to drinke of the water, which had ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177769:12"/> good effect in him, that without any paine at all hee had the benefit (the firſt day) of nature, and within a few dayes he found a ſtrange alteration in his body, his ſtomack was quickned, and his ſpirits ſtrangely revived. He continued the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the water 14. dayes, till at length he was not ſenſeſible of any defect that might cauſe him to make any longer uſe of it.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, within a ſmall time (through Gods bleſſings) meerely by this water he was reſtored to be a perfect man, and ſo continueth. This was in the yeare 1628.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Foules</hi> a gentleman of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of <hi>Edenborow,</hi> about the age of 57. yeares, throught a weakeneſſe of all his lims proceeding (as may bee ſuppoſed) from a relaxation of the ſinewes, was not able (but with much trembling) to lift his hand to his mouth, or to get on, or off his horſe but with much helpe, he came to <hi>Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resbow</hi> in the yeare 1627. where having ſtaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a moneth, drinking every morning of the <hi>Spaw</hi> ſpring, and making uſe of the Sulpher wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by way of bath at his lodging, before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted hee was able to performe all fit offices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout himſelfe, without the aide of any, and hath continued in good ſtate of body ever ſince.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Rauden</hi> of <hi>Rauden</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> had beene many yeares ſoare vexed with terrible panges, and gripings in his body, ſo that through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall extremity of his diſtemper, his fleſh was decayed, his appetite loſt, and his ſleepe very ſhort and unquet. He had uſed the adviſe of ſome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177769:13"/> of the beſt Phyſitians of the Kingdome, but fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding little or no eaſe, hee came to try what the <hi>Spaw</hi> water would doe, being then but newly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged. Not many dayes after he had drunke of the water, hee avoyded two great chaines of wormes, being either of them above a yard long, which though they ſeemed divers wormes linckt together, by the ſeverall motions in many parts at once (which had they beene, would have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to thouſands) yet were but one, of which the learned report that kinde of worme to be of a ſtrange and ſcarce credible length. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4. dayes after hee voyded 4. other ſingle wormes, great and very long, but dead; After which he voyded no more, but was freed from all manner of paine, and by degrees and ſteps aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended againe to his former beſt health, and hath continued a ſound man ever ſince.</p>
            <p>The confident knowledge hereof invited a Gentleman (a neighbour of his) called <hi>Rockley,</hi> having continued long a very infirme man, and not able by any meanes to underſtand the cauſe of his weakneſſe, to try the water, where after he had ſtaid a few dayes, there came from him 14. wormes or rather <hi>Monſtra,</hi> as ſome will tearme them, every one about an intch long and alive. Their heads were black, and their tayles tipt with black, all of them having many feet. About 6. dayes after he voyded 4. more of the like forme alive: Moſt of them hee kept alive in a boxe a few dayes which were ſeene of many with no little wonderment. Since which time hee hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177769:13"/> recovered ſtrength, and liveth now in very good health.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Vaviſour</hi> (wife to S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Vavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour</hi> Baronet of <hi>Yorkſhire</hi>) had loſt in a manner the uſe of all her lims, through what diſtemper I know not, but ſhe was brought to ſuch a degree of weakeneſſe, that child-like ſhee was rockt in a cradle: There was no meanes unaſſaied which might reinable her, but all in vaine. In this eſtate ſhe was brought to the <hi>Spaw</hi> water, by the uſe whereof (by Gods mercy) ſhee was reſtored to ſtrength and health.</p>
            <p>One <hi>William Shan</hi> of <hi>Medley</hi> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> being much troubled with the ſtopping of his water, which cauſed intollerable paine, in a deſperate mood in one of his fits (being a man of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courage) cauſed an inſtrument of iron to bee made by an ordinary Smith, about the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and length of a pack-needle. This (not any other daring to doe it) hee (boldly rather than wiſely) thruſt up into his yard, and pulling it forth violently, hee opened the paſſage, ſo that a great quantity of water with an intermixture of blood iſſued forth, by reaſon of a dangerous wound made by the inſtrument, which after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ulcerous, could by no meanes bee healed. He (as his laſt refuge) repaired to the <hi>Spaw</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where within a few dayes hee received not onely cure of his former ſtoppage of water, but was perfectly cured of his ulcer.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Walles</hi> of <hi>Copeland</hi> in the county of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> about the age of 50. yeares, being
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177769:14"/> of an extraordinary corpulencie of body, his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſpecially of a vaſte greatneſſe. For diverſe yeares, he had not beene able to goe the ſpace of an hundred yards (eſpecially if it were an aſcent) without reſting himſelfe, his breath failing him upon the leaſt extraordinary motion. By the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water hee was brought to that paſſe within three weekes, that his belly did fall to an ordinary ſize, he was able to goe from the Towne of <hi>Knaresborow</hi> to the Spring (which is a mile and an halfe, part of it being a great aſcent) without any deſire of eaſe, and hath continued ever ſince a man as able to foote it as moſt of his age.</p>
            <p>The like effect the late Right Honourable Counteſſe of <hi>Buckingham</hi> found, who this laſt Summer 1631. vouchſafed to honour the <hi>Northern Spaw</hi> with her preſence. Her infirmity (I have it from her owne mouth) was a ſhortneſſe of breath, not being able to get up an ordinary paire of ſtaires but with much difficultie of breathing, and reſting once at the leaſt. There is none will queſtion but her ample fortune was able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the choyceſt helpes of phyſick: Which failing, ſhee had recourſe to <hi>Wellingborow,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that water, (ſo much famed) was not able to performe any thing worth her ſtay. At laſt ſhe was adviſed by a learned Artiſt (who was no ſtranger to this our <hi>Spaw</hi>) to make tryall of our water. Her honour was pleaſed to tell mee (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drunke orderly of the water about tenne dayes) that ſhe found the whole frame of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177769:14"/> reduced to a very good temper, and for that particular, which occaſioned her comming to the water, ſhe did profeſſe ſeriouſly, that ſhe was well able to mount two paire of ſtaires without either ſupport, or the leaſt deſire of reſpite. The time of the yeare was ſomewhat too farre ſpent at her comming to the water (for it was the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of <hi>August</hi>) ſo that the couldneſſe of the aire, and frequent ſhowers, forc't her departure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the water could finiſh its worke, which was no ſmall prejudice to her after being.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Fareweather</hi> of the Cittie of <hi>Yorke,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Micklegate</hi> had beene long troubled with a dizineſſe in her head (call it the vertigo or what you pleaſe) ſo that if ſhee did but ſtoope to the ground (looking downewards) ſhe was ready to fall; by the uſe of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water for the ſpace of a moneth was abſolutely freed from this her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Hoyle</hi> wife to the new Lord Maior of the Citty of <hi>Yorke,</hi> after ſhe had beene the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of foure children, did fall into a ſtrange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity. Her face (for the moſt part every tenne or eleven weekes after ſhee had conceived) did ſwell and grow very red, many knobs ariſing in diverſe parts of her face. The ſwelling ſometimes was ſuch that it almoſt deprived her (for the time) of her ſight: during the continuance of which trouble ſhe miſcarried of three or foure children together. It muſt be ſuppoſed one of her ability (being happy alſo by enjoying a tender, loving husband) could want no meanes that part could
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177769:15"/> afford, but no proof or good ſucceſſe was found. She was at laſt adviſed to repaire to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> where ſhe ſtaied about 3. weekes, finding appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſignes of her bodyes alteration. Within two moneths of her returne home, it pleaſed God ſhee conceived, continuing in a conſtant ſtate of health to the time of her delivery. She hath ſince then been bleſt with diverſe children, not having the leaſt touch of her former diſtemper.</p>
            <p>A poore boy about the age of 13. yeares, had often ſtrange fits like thoſe of the Epilepſie or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſicknes, yet ſomewhat differing from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary fits of that diſeaſe, neither foaming at the mouth, nor ſhewing any diſtortions of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. He would lye (as if he had beene dead) the ſpace of a quarter of an houre without the leaſt motion. In this caſe hee had continued a yeare and more, and did uſually fall two or three times a day. Hee was brought to drinke of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water, and within ten dayes did ſo alter, that he did not fall above once in ſixe dayes ſpace. He returned home in hope of recovery, yet too ſoone if my adviſe might have taken place; but the party that brought him thither, told me hee was not able to ſtay in regard of the charge.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Sadler</hi> daughter to that ſame reverend ſage of the Law, S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> (let her pardon me that I cloſe the relations of the <hi>Spaw</hi> with her name, who for her worth and excellent parts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to bee rank't and equalled with the beſt of her ſexe) came to the <hi>Spaw</hi> in the yeare 1630. Her diſtemper (as neare as I can enforme my
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177769:15"/> felfe) was a long continued fixed paine in her head. It is very probable that ſhee received be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by the waters uſe, which encouraged her to repaire to the water againe the laſt yeare 1631. And pitty it were ſhe ſhould not finde good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, ſhee ſhewed her ſelfe ſo rare a patterne of patience, in attending the iſſue of 6. weekes ſtay, not any one that I have obſerved, proceeding in the whole courſe in drinking of the water, with ſuch conſtant obſervation of all thoſe rules which are requiſite to be obſerved by thoſe who expect benefit by the water.</p>
            <p>And now having finiſhed what I thinke fit to inſtance concerning this our <hi>Spaw</hi> water, I will adde a few experiments of the Sulpher ſpring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maud Bogge</hi> (for by that name ſhe is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne) a woman of an ordinary condition, dwelling in the City of <hi>Yorke;</hi> about the age of 50. yeares, had a ſwelling about her Ancle, which had continued long. The place was for the moſt part very red, and hard, whereunto was applied diverſe meanes by the Surgeons to bring it to a head, but nothing avayled. Her paine did dayly increaſe, the part was growne monſterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great, whereby ſhee began to looſe the uſe of her lime. She was at length adviſed to goe to the Sulpher ſpring neare <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> whether with much adoe ſhe was brought on horſeback. The next day after her comming ſhee drunke li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally of the water, which purged her in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner, and at night ſhe bathed her legge in the water at her lodging. This courſe ſhe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177769:16"/> for three dayes, during which time the ſwelling abated very much, and ſhe was able the fourth day to tread on the ground ſo boldly and firmely, that without expecting any further ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the water, ſhee returned to the Citty of <hi>Yorke</hi> on foot, as if ſhee ſcorned any other helpe, and within a weeke ſhee was ſo perfectly cured, that diverſe who had ſeene her ſwelled legge, did admire to ſee her trot up and downe the City, as if ſhe had never ayled any thing. This was in the the yeare 1627. This Summer being 1631. I ſpoke with her at <hi>Yorke</hi> from whom I had her ſtory, D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Deane</hi> and diverſe others in <hi>Yorke</hi> taking ſpeciall notice of it.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1629. there came a poore man to make uſe of the Sulphur ſpring, whoſe name and abode I have not had the opertunity to learne. Hee had a great ſwelling in his knee which had continued long. The place was exceeding hard to feele to, &amp; growne over with haire, nor could the force of any medicine make it to yeeld to any abatement or ſuppuration. He drunke of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayly, which purged him, and bathed his leg often in it: within leſſe then a fortnight the part did ſenſiblely ſoften, and ſoone after did breake, whence iſſued a great number of ſmall wormes, to the amazement of diverſe. Freed from theſe, he was much refreſhed, and within a few dayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his home by all appearance a ſound man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> F. F.</note> A noble Knight (who lived then neare <hi>Knaresborow</hi>) tooke (as there was good cauſe) ſpeciall notice of this ſtrange cure, whoſe unble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177769:16"/> reputation is a ſufficient warrant to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me in the publiſhing of it.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Benſon</hi> who dwelleth neare the ſpring, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured me a poore woman had received the like cure in one of her breaſts, whereof he was a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more familiar then for poore people to repaire to this ſpring, moſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (that have the patience to ſtay) receiving cure of old ſoares, and ulcerated parts. What inward deſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes this water doth properly reſpect, hath not yet (which is great pitty) been judiciouſly examined: but that it may be uſefully applied, this one fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing inſtance may fully ſatisfie.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Smith</hi> a Shoomaker dwelling in the City of <hi>Yorke,</hi> was extreamely overgrowne with the Scurvey, ſo that he was in ſome danger of his life, uſuall medicines nothing availing. Hee was at length adviſed by a learned Scholler in the City (by profeſſion a Divine,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>G.</hi>
               </note> yet verſed of late in phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall notions) to ſend for the Sulphur ſpring wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his houſe, which he not very willingly did, thinking it a hard taske to drink water in the cold of winter. His ordinary draught was halfe a pint in the morning, which had ſuch good ſucceſſe in him, that within leſſe then a moneth he was by this and other meanes quit of his diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>The like effect a good old man in the City ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented to his great reliefe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr</hi> A. P.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Loe here two ſprings of admirable operations! And if an exact Sumetritian by the proportion of <hi>Hercules</hi> his foote bee able to collect the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177769:17"/> whole fabrick of his body, why may not the learned (whoſe ſerious thoughts are bent upon the theory of natures ſecrets) from theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples deduce excellent concluſions of large and ample uſe.</p>
            <p>I had thought to ſhut up this diſcourſe but that I am loath to ſmoother any thing that may tend to the publique good.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who have obſerved the wonders of this our happy Ile, have taken notice of a Spring ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted underneath the Caſtle of <hi>Knaresborow,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the dropping Well, famous for the turning whatſoever is caſt into it or caſually falls in (as Moſſe, leaves, ſticks, and the like) into ſtone: whereupon it is that this Spring is viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of many by way of admiration. But time hath of late diſcovered a phyſicall uſe of this water, namely, that it is an infallible cure for a flixe.</p>
            <p>This yeare 1631. it was my chance to bee a witneſſe of this particular. A Miniſter of <hi>Yorke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> one <hi>Greatheed,</hi> came to <hi>Knaresborow</hi> to give his attendance on a noble Gentlewoman, whoſe infirmitie did crave the aide of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water. He (not intending to drinke of the water ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) thought hee might ſafely now and then (as many do for companies ſake) take a few draughts of the <hi>Spaw</hi> water within a weekes ſtay (by what accident I know not) hee was overtaken with a violent flixe, which continued three dayes in ſuch a degree of exceſſe, that there was juſt cauſe to feare. At that time there was happily in the houſe a Phyſician of good note, one Dr. <hi>Webbe</hi> (a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177769:17"/> Gentleman of extraordinary curious parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his exact knowledge in his profeſſion, to whom theſe <hi>Northerne</hi> waters are indebted for his carefull examination of them, and his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to advance their dew fame) whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe being craved (and time it was to adviſe, for the party was brought ſo weak, that he was ſtept into a degree of convulſions) he (out of former experience in a noble Lady in the ſame caſe, who (all other meanes failing) had received preſent helpe by this dropping Well) preſently cauſed him to drinke a draught of the ſaid water, which without dallying inſtantly ſtaied the flixe, ſo that within a few dayes he became a ſtrong man.</p>
            <p>Theſe fore rehearſed truths conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may not <hi>Knaresborow</hi> challenge any place in <hi>Europe</hi> for variety of uſefull and rare ſprings? If it be objected by any (for there is a ſnarling gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that have ever ſomething to ſay (though to no great purpoſe) againſt any thing) that they have met with thoſe who have beene at theſe rare waters, and have found little or no benefit by them. I anſwer, was there ever yet any medicine heard or read of, of that unvalluable worth that was an aſſured Catholicon againſt all diſeaſes? I but (ſay they) your waters have failed even in theſe particular inſtances which you have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. I grant it, and yet no derogation from the waters efficatious uſe. A diſeaſe is curable at one time, which at another admits no poſſibilitie. <hi>Veniente occurrite morbo. Sero medicina paratur, &amp;c.</hi> A young twigge may eaſily be pul'd up, but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177769:18"/> let it grow, and there will be much adoe to make it wag. If it be replied that ſuch as have repaired to the water, were but newly entred into their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and yet returned no better then they came thither: without any long quarreling about the matter, I ſay it is a wonder that diverſe who drinke of the water returne not worſe. For how many (if they were well examined) prepare their bodies, which how groſſe an omiſſion it is, let the learned judge? Beſides how few are there who keepe an ordinary diet? How many depart (in a chafe) from the water, becauſe they have not found themſelves in a weeke as ſound as a Bell; when as (the world knowes) their bodies have beene crack't and craſie for many yeares?</p>
            <p>And yet theſe gallants (gilty perhaps of all theſe errors) complaine of want of vertue in theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when the greateſt want is in themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refractory and averſe in obſerving a metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall courſe, without which the moſt elaborate and choice recepts that ever were, are liable to diſparagements.</p>
            <p>But I have done ſquabbling with theſe humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts, and for the benefit of the more ingenious ſort, I deſire that (for their owne ſakes) they would (if neceſſity hale them to theſe waters, for they are no more to be played withall, than any other phyſick) take notice of theſe following cautions, which require a neceſſary obſervance of all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, undertake not thy ſelfe to judge of thine owne body, what correſpondence the water
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177769:18"/> may have with thy infirmitie: but repaire to the learned Phyſitian, to whom it properly belongs to determine of thee.</p>
            <p>Secondly, being once reſolved to uſe the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, fit thy ſelf for it by taking a day or two before thou drinke of it, ſome ſuch apt preparative as beſt may ſute with the quality and nature of thy diſtemper. For this purpoſe adviſe with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Phyſician (eſpecially one that is acquainted with the waters uſe) for hee it is (and onely hee) that knoweth how to vary preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to apply to every one that which is moſt proper.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, reſolve during the time of thy drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the water to keep an orderly diet in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, avoyding all meates of groſſe nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in the quantity let thy meales be ſpare but eſpecially thy ſuppers. And if that at other times thou art indulgent to thy appetite, now doe as <hi>Salomon</hi> adviſeth in another caſe. Put thy knife to thy throat and reſtraine thy former liberty: which ſtrictneſſe would be obſerved (to very good purpoſe) a moneth after thy departure from the water, according to the opinion of the beſt obſervers.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, keep thy ſelfe (according to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) in ſuch a degree of temper, that neither im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate heate nor coldneſſe of the aire offend thee, but of the latter there is the more feare, the mornings being often cold. The place and ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe waters doe a little too much expoſe all conditions of people that repaire to them to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177769:19"/> the inconvenience of a cold piercing aire, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were to bee wiſht that thoſe of the more tender ſort, whether of ſexe, education, or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall weakeneſſe, would (during the time of their drinking the water) every morning when they goe to the fountain be armed with an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent warme garment, which if it be not put off till the water have had its operation (which for the moſt part is four hours after the drinking, unleſſe the day prove more then ordinary warme) were not amiſſe. For I am perſwaded theſe ſame ſlaſh't carbonadoed ſutes ſo much in faſhion, are no ſmall prejudice to moſt that weare them. And yet how many are there both of yeares (though not of diſcretion in this) and of weake conſtitutions (but more weake judgements) who (rather then they will not bee at the command of that ſame grand dominering Tyrant <hi>Mounſieur Deformite</hi>) care not how ſoone they leave the world rather then live out of the faſhion, be it never ſo uſeleſſe and monſtrous.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, attempt not to drinke theſe waters, but with a prepared patience to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the iſſue of their opperation, according to the uſuall time allotted for them, which ought to bee a moneth at leaſt. The precipitate and haſty parting from them is no ſmall cauſe why many finde not the benefit which they expect. In the cloſe before thou leave the place, it is very convenient to take a gentle purge of the nature of thy preparative.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if in the uſe of the water it doth plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare to thee that it worketh effectually,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177769:19"/> croſſe not the courſe of it by an intermixture of any other phyſick, whoſe ayde ought onely to bee craved when the water is wanting in its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, or doth produce ſome extraordinary ſumptomes, and then the learned hand of Arte may be a great meanes to ſupport and relieve the weakeneſſe of nature, or any other accidentall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience.</p>
            <p>Other concurring circumſtances there are, not unworthythy obſervation in drinking the water which are learnedly and accurately ſet downe in the <hi>Spadacrene,</hi> whereunto I referre thee for a full ſatisfaction both of the nature and uſe of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Let me only put thee in minde that the moſt proper time to uſe the water is from the middle of <hi>Iune</hi> to the end of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that late years have brought to light in diverſe parts of the Kingdome, waters of neare alliance to this our <hi>Northerne Spaw:</hi> but by the beſt enquiry I can make, it is plaine they muſt all vaile bonet to this of ours, for fullneſſe of minerall and activety of ſpirits, be they what they will, whether thoſe of <hi>Wellingborow, Tun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Briſtow,</hi> or any other. And that which makes this our water not patternable (beſides its owne worth) is the confluence and variety of Springs, that (by way of attendance) environ it. For I dare bee bold to affirme that within the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of two miles, I will ſhew ſeaven ſeverall Springs all of diverſe natures, aparantly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable either in taſte, or ſmell. So that (I am perſwaded) had theſe waters but the happineſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177769:20"/> to be honoured one Summer with the preſence, and examination of ſome ſuch learned Artiſt as D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Iordin</hi> (who in his late exact diſcourſe of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall waters, and baths, ſhewes he hath a ſupar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative capacity of diving into the bowels of the earth, and expoſing to light thoſe hidden miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that lie lockt up in the boſome of that dark Element) not onely this Kingdome, but moſt neighboring Nations would troope unto them, having once received allowance by the divulging of his or the like judicious pen.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all that is wanting to theſe waters. There is a ſtaine unthought of, which time I hope waſh away, for it is a ſhame it hath ſo long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who neighbour neareſt to theſe waters, are an indigenous poore people, not able to ſtep out of the roade of their laborious calling, being plaine husbandmen and cottagers, and therefore it cannot be expected they ſhould accommodate them in their many uſefull concernments where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are moſt groſſely defective. What un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely ſhifts have I ſeen many ſtrangers of note put to for want of a convenient place of retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? How is the company forc't ſometimes to leave the place for want of ſhelter to defend them from the guſts of many a cold morning, wherein though all doe ſuffer, yet thoſe that are weake (I aſſure my ſelfe) receive more prejudice by the piercing bleake aire, then benefit by the water? For if in the ſmalleſt phyſicall preparatives that are preſcribed, we are fitly charged to beware of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177769:20"/> cold, or any impetuouſneſſe of the aire, how much more in the frequent draughts of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is apt (with ſome violence) now and then to open the body? And that which is ſtrange, of many ſcores that meet in a morning and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for the moſt part an houre together, there is ſcarce a ſeate provided for halfe a dozen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them. Is it not a ſhame that the Sulphur ſpring (whereof many of the beſt ſort have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to drinke) ſhould lie open for the promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous uſe of all ſorts, without any due order obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the keeping of it, ſo that poore Lazer, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent people, doe dayly environ it, whoſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid rags lie ſcattered up and downe, and it is to bee doubted whether they doe not waſh their ſoares, &amp; cleanſe their beſmeared clouts (though unſeene) where diverſe after dippe their cups to drinke. Not that I would have the poore debard the uſe of the ſpring, (God forbid that thoſe ſhould not bee moſt eſpecially cared for, who are leaſt able to care for themſelves) but I ſee no cauſe why the uſe may not be reduced to a better order. And if it be doubted that this ſpring will hardly bee accommodated for all ſorts (which I make no doubt but it may, being carefully gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) I will undertake within a quarter of a mile to finde one or two of the ſame equall worth which may be appropriated for the meaner ſort. From this &amp; the like abuſe it is that diverſe juſtly complaine, and wiſh that ſome one might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by authority to mannage theſe waters, and to provide all things neceſſary for their more fit
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177769:21"/> uſe, conditionally that allowance might be made annually by all ſuch as have recourſe to them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their qualities. But if wiſhes would ſerve the turne, this (with many more neglects) had found redreſſe long ſince. That which I thinke worthy of complaint is, that of ſo many of note who have received benefit by theſe waters, nay ſome of them, who (under God) owe their lives to them, there is not one that hath left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde any memoriall of their gratitude worth the remembrance. Of ten Leapers, there was one that returned to give thanks, (which was the only fee that was expected for his cure) and hee alone was ſtampt upon as worthy his recovery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nahaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> by the dim light of nature could ſee that his reſtoring to health would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a large recompence, and therefore he came furniſhed with gifts of great worth, which hee preſſingly (though refuſed) tendered the Prophet. And I verily thinke that there are ſome now li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, who could they have beene aſſured (before their comming to theſe waters) of ſuch a latitude of unexpected health as now they enjoy by them, they would have purchaſed it at halfe their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates. Shall after ages then take notice of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as have beene raiſed from their weary ſicke couches to perfect ſtrength, and no ſigne of thankefullneſſe remaining, but becauſe they have beene put to ſtraights at their being at the waters, muſt others hereafter ſhift as they have done? A benefit (let it derive it ſelfe whence it will) doth ever (in an ingenious ſpirit) traine after it a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177769:21"/> tacite and innominate obligation of a gratefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and implicitly challenge a proportionable retribution, according to the quality of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and benefit received. Let it never bee ſaid therefore (yee eſpecially (whoſoever yee are) whoſe eſtates raiſe you (like <hi>Saul</hi>) the ſhoulders and upwards above others) that ye are indebted to the <hi>Spaw</hi> for your recoveries, and that ye left it as naked of all fit ſupplement as ye found it, but ſtirre up one another to give a largeſſe to make the place more apt for after times, both to invite ſtrangers thither, and comfort thoſe of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſort with ſome fit accommodations, who are neceſſitated to uſe the water. Yee that have beene at theſe waters know the naturall rudeneſſe of the place, how voyde it is of all proviſions, and Chriſtians (of all others) ſhould remember, that they are not borne for themſelves, but that they ought to caſt an eye upon ſucceeding ages.</p>
            <p>But if ye will leave this worke for others now your owne turnes are ſerved, yet ſomething (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old ſaying) hath ſome ſavour: Me thinkes the neighbouring poore of the place (who are not a few) might taſte of your bounty whom ye ſhall finde the beſt treaſurers and ſtewards of your liberality. Or looke upon ſome poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Pariſhes that border upon the <hi>Spaw</hi> (which ſave the ordinary ſervice ſcarce once in a yeare know what the comfortable refection of a teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſter meaneth) what a ſort of ſtarved ſoules there are for want of the word diſpenſed to them, and by ſupplying that defect, God ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177769:22"/> be honoured, and a bleſſing will be the readier to attend the waters. Yet why doe I ſtrive to rouze and ſtimulate your beneficence, by preſcribing to you wayes of thankefulneſſe? Where true charity is, it needs no prompting, but can finde a thouſand dry channels to moiſten with its wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtreames. I hope this little blaſt I have made bold to give, will be ſufficient either in you or ſome other (if the world be not drawne dry of generouſnes) to make your expreſſions breake forth into a flame of bounty.</p>
            <p>To conclude (for my ambition to promote the common good, hath perhaps (as ſome may thinke) cauſed me to expatiate a little too farre) ſince it is undeniable by the preceding particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that theſe waters are worth the cheriſhing.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ceaſe then who ere thou art, (whoſe ſnarling vaine</l>
               <l>Will not permit thee, ſee thy Country's gaine;)</l>
               <l>To ſtaine theſe waters with thy bleare-ey'd looke,</l>
               <l>Or mis-interpret this truth-ſpeaking Booke.</l>
               <l>But if thy dreggy and diſtemper'd bloud,</l>
               <l>So cloud thy braine thou canſt not ſee what's good:</l>
               <l>Repaire to theſe our waters, which can quell,</l>
               <l>Thoſe miſtie vapours and all fogs diſpell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye Chimiſts whoſe high-perching wits aſpire,</l>
               <l>T' extract the quinteſcence of all by fire,</l>
               <l>Dreame ye no more of what was never knowne:</l>
               <l>(But by ſuppoſe) that all effecting ſtone</l>
               <l>The gate to wealth, and what mans heart can thinke,</l>
               <l>Which makes your brains to ſweat, your pens with inke</l>
               <l>To blur your papers, for ye doe but leave</l>
               <l>Behinde darke miſts of words that doe deceive.</l>
               <l>Here would ye ſpend a few of theſe loſt dayes</l>
               <l>Ye now beſtow, O with what worthy praiſe,</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:177769:22"/>
               <l>Might ye endeare your Country's good and finde</l>
               <l>Matter well worth your labour, to unbinde:</l>
               <l>By your extractions thoſe ſame linkes and chaines</l>
               <l>Of hidden ſecrets which as yet remaines</l>
               <l>Vntide, that their proportion duely knowne,</l>
               <l>Their uſe might be divulg'd to every one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye bold brazen ſcattered Empericks,</l>
               <l>Who purge mens purſes with your cheating tricks:</l>
               <l>Leave to diſport your ſelves with your conceats,</l>
               <l>Of jugling powders that can worke all feats.</l>
               <l>The learned know, and who beſt judge muſt grant,</l>
               <l>Y'are groſſe impoſtures, blinde and ignorant,</l>
               <l>Come ſit you downe, by theſe our waters bankes,</l>
               <l>Note well their rare effects, what ſeverall rankes</l>
               <l>Of ſtarved bodies here receive their cure,</l>
               <l>Which would ye marke in time ye might procure:</l>
               <l>By your obſerving to direct and guide,</l>
               <l>Such as to long ſad weakeneſſe haue beene tide.</l>
               <l>For here are wonders of no common ſtraine,</l>
               <l>Diſeaſes cur'd without or griefe or paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſhaking Palſy here gets ſteady lims,</l>
               <l>The giddy Megrim and the braine that ſwims:</l>
               <l>The Vlcer of the Kidneyes and the ſtone,</l>
               <l>(That is not fixt) all ſuch as make their moane,</l>
               <l>Of perturb'd fancie riſing from the Spleane,</l>
               <l>The viſcuous bowels that want making cleane;</l>
               <l>Diſtemper of the Livers fiery heat,</l>
               <l>Weake indigeſtions both of drinke and meate.</l>
               <l>Flixes, Cathars, obſtructions in their kindes,</l>
               <l>Diſturbing painefull flutulent groſſe windes:</l>
               <l>Wormes of all ſorts, the Epilepſe, the ſicke,</l>
               <l>Who plainely doe appeare they'r Aſthmatick.</l>
               <l>Theſe and what not that Art could ever cure,</l>
               <l>Nature preſents them with a water pure:</l>
               <l>Which fitly us'd in its due ſeaſon can,</l>
               <l>Reſtore a dying to a living man.</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:177769:23"/>
               <l>Had <hi>Gallen</hi> met with waters ſuch as theſe,</l>
               <l>Or that ſame grave well-vers't <hi>Hypocrates,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or thoſe <hi>Arabian</hi> ſages, learned men,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Raſes, Averroes,</hi> or that <hi>Avicen:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe with the reſt were they alive to ſee,</l>
               <l>Our waters how they ſute to each degree,</l>
               <l>Of age and ſexe, and with what eaſe they doe,</l>
               <l>Effect their operation, they would wooe,</l>
               <l>To be ſpectators of theſe rare events,</l>
               <l>Nature (unheard of) to the world preſents.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My pen's too dull, to blaze them I have done,</l>
               <l>'Tis vaine to prove ther's brightneſſe in the Sun.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
